it probably goes without saying that as
a programmer you need to edit files you
need to change files you need to write a
lot of text right and you're going to
need an editor for that and we've talked
about
using uh the raw editor in GitHub we've
talked about
using um the
is the best editor for programming this
is probably one of the most problematic
click bity kind of titles that you're
ever going to see for me and there's a
reason that the editors that I'm going
to talk about are are there and um
there's going to be all kinds of hate in
the comments because probably one of the
most emotional topics that anybody can
ever bring up on any kind of stream is
what is your editor in fact um I used to
ask that question when vetting
candidates for uh to work in Tech um
when I worked at nike.com And I was
asked to be the technical subject matter
expert and vet the new candidates to see
whether you know how good they were and
one of the questions that I would almost
always ask is what is your editor and
why did you use it and believe it or not
I mean is that enough information to
know whether someone's going to be a
good developer no but it definitely
gives an insight into to how their brain
is working what kind of coding they
prefer what their workflow is is based
on whether they're going to be able to
integrate well with the team that I'm on
depending on how they get their work
done so the question about what editor
to use and how to install it and all of
that thing is a very telling question
and um I do have a story about this so
uh the story is uh one of the guys that
I that I mentored he was actually
Psychology major who couldn't get a job
and spent a couple years with me uh and
then ended up getting a starting job
salary job for $100,000 a year and he
was selected to be one of the interns in
the first round and then he was hired
after being an intern and during his job
interview I've told the story before but
during his job interview uh the person
giving him the interview apologized for
using an editor their editor and saying
oh I only use this and the person that
was being interviewed was using an
editor that the interviewer considered
to be an indication of being Superior uh
because because and the the choice of
editor is is whether you whether I like
it or not whether you like it or not in
the tech world the editor that you
choose says a lot about you and it
carries a lot of weight and you know the
kind of editor you same with Linux
distributions or languages you choose to
learn all of these things but the editor
that you pick says a lot about you and
it can actually the editor you can pick
can actually be considered a flex
depending on the circumstances so I I
we're not going to really get into that
but I really want you to understand it
because if you pick if you you know you
could end up I I know this is really
horrible to say it but you could end up
tanking uh you know your rep with with a
particular group because you know you
didn't say the right editor now for the
record I think that if somebody's going
to judge you based on your editor for a
job position that they should no longer
be working in that company and they
should not be in charge of hiring people
because your editor at the end of the
day most of the time nine times out of
10 the editor that you use and you
choose to use does not impact your
ability to perform most tech jobs
however there are a couple very specific
positions that critically depend on
specific editors and being able to use
them and that is a really good
opportunity for me to um to actually
wrap up this video
okay so does your editor matter your
editor absolutely does matter okay so
let's let's clean let's actually dive in
before the video is completely over and
let's talk about what is the best editor
for the job and what editor should you
pick uh in general depending on the job
and whether you need to learn it or not
and I'm going to go through I'm going to
go through all of the main editors I'm
not going to talk about the edge case
editors really right now I'm going to
talk talk about the main editors so so
here they are uh the the absolute number
one editor on the planet right now is uh
Visual Studio code everybody uses it and
we'll do another video where we install
it uh but here it is Visual Studio
code um and this this relates to I mean
as soon as you download visual studio
code the first thing you'll notice is
that Visual Studio code is the same it's
exactly the same as
github.io code let's talk about that why
is Visual Studio code the best the best
editor for for that kind of thing or
vscodium here we go we got people with
opinions already vscodium just so you
know is a free version of Visual Studio
code it's not owned by Microsoft um that
is not particularly better it's just
different uh people have very very
strong opinions on that they do not want
Microsoft Telemetry they don't want to
give Microsoft credit uh even though
Microsoft built you know uh Beal Studio
code uh from scratch it's it's it's
using a bunch of Graphics Technologies
it's using I don't I don't really want
to get into it it's using uh electron
which is a very controversial technology
with regard to bloat and amount of
memory usage and uh actually electron is
is responsible for lots of applications
that you may not even know about but it
definitely has code um so it doesn't
matter none of that matters you are a
beginner and I'm talking to you and you
must learn I'm telling you as a
beginner if you have never even tried
out Visual Studio code people will look
at you a scance they'll look at you like
you've never used vs code ever you never
even fired it up to try it out no so
even if you don't like it even if you
totally hate it and you don't think it's
the best tool for your job which would
be my case even for web development I do
not use it um there's a good chance
you're going to need to use it there
there's another good reason that you
might be able to a lot of beginners love
it um I actually pull disclosure um
Visual Studio code has a builtin shared
coding environment strategy and I
actually for several years um in
2020 I uh and 21 I met with the core
team of the visual studio code project
uh to give feedback because they were
developing their pa programming where
you have two people literally with
little cursors jumping around all over
the screen it's really cool and I was
able to use that from my desk and and
they were coding from their desk and as
a mentor I was able to literally show
them where they should code and where
they should code elsewhere and if you're
doing any kind of remote mentoring with
like oneon-one or one on two it's
absolutely fantastic for that now there
are other ways to do this using the
terminal and other things and we'll talk
about that as well but out out of the
gate Visual Studio code is extremely
powerful for collaborative editing so
that remember we talked about best tool
for the job right why you might want to
pick this editor if you if you're
working with a team that's doing a bunch
of
collaboration and that's doing you know
this kind of thing where they're they're
they're all look you need to be able to
look at the same code at the same time
and that's really up to you to decide if
that's even needed if you're using
something like git and GitHub then you
can just share that and you can see all
those commits in the pr process and you
don't really need that real real time
editing right um another huge advantage
of Visual Studio code of course is that
it's localized that means you're running
it on your computer and I I want to
pause on this point because there is a
huge movement I I'll make another video
about it but I'm just going to say don't
use cloud-based editors it's it's a bad
idea what happens when you're in the
airplane what happens when you're
outside of range how are you going to
work on your code you can't right so if
your if your team or you are dependent
on the internet to do your development
you will fail the whole point of G is to
be able to down I'll make a whole video
on that just don't do it Visual Studio
code is a local editor you download it
you install it you run it and you
synchronize your changes up to the cloud
and then other people can pull down your
changes and when you want to you can
actually if you're online you can
collaborate with a bunch of other people
um there are two other really
spectacularly great reasons to use
Visual Studio code one of them is
already one that we saw uh when we were
doing our previewing let me show you
again if I can find it where are you
here we go so so this is Visual Studio
code running in the web browser uh as
this is you know we talked there another
video about this this is
images and that's where that Elliot imag
came from before so you have live
previewing of tables and all kinds of
good stuff um oops that's not it here we
go um there you go there's the live
previewing so live previewing is a major
reason to use vs um Visual Studio code
um and the third one I can't immediately
show you we're going to do a whole video
on this the third one is because Visual
Studio code comes with lots of
extensions and PE some people will say
the extensions are a downside
uh I mean there are thousands and
thousands of extensions you can add and
by the way if you add too many of those
extensions you end up blowing up right
your your takes your forever for your
Editor to run but those extensions are a
very solid reason to use vs code um the
the extensions um in a world of
graphical editors I I was going to say
Graphics is is one of the advantages but
it's kind of a given um in in the world
of graphical editing um you know having
an extension is a very valuable thing
for example we're going to use uh an
extension called live preview which
contains its own little teeny tiny web
server so that you can on your computer
without any internet connection you can
preview uh any web development in fact
uh I use this at a private school at
woodlon uh to do we had a there was an
after school program for 4050 people and
they were all doing game development web
game development and they were able to
do it using phaser.js which I'll make
another video about because they were
hosting from their own laptops so they
had live server running every time they
made a change to their game it
immediately refreshed their web browser
and it showed the new game changes
immediately whether it be dragging in a
uh uh a new skin for for their you know
platformer you know Avatar or whatever
it immediately showed them the changes
so so the extensions including live
stream you know the live previewing
those are fantastic ways to do that can
they be can that be done with with uh
notepad++ not Plus+ plus is is another
relatively minimalistic one uh let me
let me mention the other ones I I spend
a lot of time on vs code because that's
the one I recommend but let me mention
just so you at least know they exist
about a half dozen other graphical e
kinds of editors that I do not recommend
so the uh the one that started at all is
called Sublime uh that is a combination
of C++ and python it's highly
proprietary it hasn't gone through any
updates in a very long time time um
Sublime gets the sublime Su Al gets the
credit for inspiring this minimalistic
editor kind of World um it it is still a
great editor but it's just it's if you
read through the news groups it's not
being maintained uh the the core
contributors are like got really pissed
off because the person's refusing to do
it because it's highly proprietary um
it's a pretty fair I don't know that
it's ever been officially said but it's
pretty fair to say that Microsoft copied
verbatim the look and feel of of sublime
which was the first lightweight code
editor um graphical code editor and and
then and then you've got uh all of the
other ones in the same vein you have
Adobe brackets which is just a adobe's
version of the same thing um you have I
mean there's what's the other one uh
emac is not graphical absolutely not no
it isn't and we're not going to we'll
talk about emex and when we talk about
terminal editors we'll get into that um
so so those are the main those are the
main editors uh Adam that's the one
thank you for reminding me so Adam
people still use Adam a lot so the the
the the editors that are in the same
vein that are head-to-head against each
other are uh Visual Studio code and
please don't forget code at the end
Visual Studio is a completely different
Beast you don't even want to look at
that thing unless you're doing C++ or C
development for Microsoft projects in my
opinion or net perhaps you just don't
want to mess with that um so BS Studio
code right and then and then you have
Sublime which which which inspired you
have brackets which is Adobes you have
atom and they're all largely the same
they're all very much the same sort of
thing so in terms of a graphical browser
uh we talked about the reasons to use a
graphical browser and which graphical
browser for you to pick up and which one
to use um there's the other editor
graphical browsers you might hear of is
something called Eclipse which is
usually primarily a Java technology um
really olds and you probably won't be
required to use that unless you're
working for uh a company doing doing
Java development but um that probably
doesn't include you so V Studio code and
that is the world of graphical browsers
now we're going to now in the same video
I probably should break this up but I'm
not going to now let's cover Jeet brains
okay that's a good one so all of I'm
glad let's let's let's stay with the
graphic browsers I forgot Jeet brains
completely so um if you're doing go
development there are uh all the jet
brains stuff there's there's
goand um there you know when when it
comes to uh what's the uh what's the
cotlin browser what's the cotlin browser
PHP Storm jet
brains um God what is it I forget the
other one anyway Jeet brains makes great
great great editors goand is is arguably
the best uh graphic browser graphic
editor for go uh many real serious go
Pros use it um I don't I I'm a command
line guy which we'll get to that in a
second uh I
idea um I forget it there's Colin is
another is a is a brand of java it's not
Java it's its own language so so that's
the thing um I is somebody else in the
comments if if I miss a I'm obviously
I'm going to miss a lot of brows a lot
of editors right so please put the
editors in the comments that I have
missed uh the main takeaway from this in
terms of graphical ones is the purpose
of this video has been here's why I
think you should use a graphical editor
on occasion and the main reasons to use
one and here's here's why I think that
BS Studio code is the best one not just
the most popular I still think it's the
best okay and then the the the the
eclipse and that means yeah and then so
the rest of this video from now on out
is going to be about terminal based
editors and I was going to make a
separate video about terminal based
editors but I'm just going to mention
them right now um because and inevitably
someone's going to run across this video
and go why didn't you mention blah blah
blah blah blah and I'm going to tell you
right now we are not going to dig down
deep into the terminal based browsers
because we haven't covered the terminal
yet okay um obviously the most popular
of the terminal berries browser uh did I
say it better browser I meant editor the
most the most popular of the terminal
based editors continues to be neovim uh
there it's you know I do not like Neo
viim I'm a Vim guy and Vim is the one
you need to learn Vim is by far the most
popular neovim is a new fangled version
of Vim that that is nice and all but it
it it diverges from Vim in ways that are
not required um the all the advantages
the advantages of a terminal based
browser are fundamentally how well does
it work with the system not can I have a
Graphic user can I have a graphic
everything from my graphic user uh
browser um you my guey browser editor
everything from my guey editor can I not
have that also as in my terminal base
you know editor and my biggest complaint
about terminal base uh editor piics is
that people pick terminal editors um
using the same criteria that they would
use for a graphical editor and and a
certain point you might just use you
know vs code with extensions right um
and so so the the the the two oldest and
biggest the the head the biggest fight
in the terminal land have been VI versus
emac and that fight has been going back
to the
1980s late 80s right so emac which is
all things to all people versus a VI
which is a visual mode of a command line
terminal Ed which has been on every
single unic System since it was invented
um which is one of the reasons I think
you should learn it and we're going to
talk about that a lot more when we get
to the terminal um I tell you what man
the when you get when you're talking
about you know like terminal terminal
selection you're talking about a holy
war I mean you can literally have people
like threaten violence uh over you know
telling them that their terminal based
editor is bad and and attacking them I
mean they get really really bent out of
shape um and you know Richard stalman
who invented emac um has been you know
in it forever uh he calls VI the number
of the Beast it's sainton and all kinds
of stuff and look VI is on every system
emac is not and my primary criteria for
use of a terminal-based editor is How
likely am I to find it on the system and
how easily can I add it if it is not on
the system and you know Ed which is
literally the standard Unix editor um
its visual mode is VI so I think VI and
Bim should be the very first things you
should learn uh in fact you should learn
Ed as well you should learn this is my
my we're going to go through this later
um we're going to learn
Ed um we're going to learn uh Ed we're
going to learn uh VI then we're going to
learn vim and then we'll look at neovim
on top of that and if you if you layer
them on top of each other like that
you'll end up knowing how each one works
and you can decide how much
customization you want to have because
you're not going to find Neo on any
system ever you're going to have to
install it so whereas VI might very
likely be on every system you ever use
so when you use a terminal based editor
the selection criteria in my opinion
changes dramatically right if if you
know that you're only going to be you
just prefer the terminal over a graphic
user interface and you know you're going
to be on that system forever and you're
going to customize one single container
or one single system or one single
desktop Linux machine or whatever you
know you're going to be on that system
maybe you're a physicist maybe you're a
machine learning person maybe you're a
game developer you know that you have
the you have everything you need on your
own system and you don't have to be good
on multiple systems then yes at that
point I would say look seriously at emac
most of the emac users that I run into
are academics and they are uh software
developers so the Linux team L Linux T
bals uses emac a version of slim down
version of emex um people who are
maintaining huge code bases people that
are on the same system all the time who
don't have to bounce around on lots of
systems they almost always you know um
again you know the academic world Buist
people like that they love emac because
it's extremely powerful and it's built
on lisp which is an amazing language uh
a very functional uh language that that
they love to use and it's fantastic but
once you learn it you I mean you you
know you're in that ecosystem and so if
if you know you're going to be on that
machine and you're only going to be
doing a thing then consider consider
that right and then in the same vein is
neovim neovim is is is basically Vim on
steroids where they've added a whole
plugin architecture in Lua and a bunch
of other stuff taking the whole idea of
VI and rewrote rewrote all of VI in evim
in in um in in Lua and that allows for
lots of expansion and everything but in
my opinion if you're going to use VI
that's just for people who really really
really love Vim they just like the Vim
interface and everything um you know in
terms of plug-in extensions and all that
stuff Li you I would say emac completely
destroys neovim on that front because
it's been around a lot longer it has a
much R richer ecosystem uh of plugins if
if you're into the plug-in World um if
you're a Vim user like I am then I my
plugins are shell scripts and I am using
the I'm using the Vim magic of using the
the wand command to bring in my shell
scripts and integrate them into my my
editor flow and a lot of people who
reach for neovim uh or even emac don't
know about that they don't know how to
integrate their Unix filter commands
from the command line and we will be
talking at length about all of that so
you can make a solid decision for
yourself um uh and so uh so that's um
what extens you the text editor I great
I don't think you need extensions in a
text editor as we've got we got many
people participating in the chat already
um editors are a very very very personal
thing and um I would just I'm G to end
this video with a plea a plea to
everyone who talks about editors um the
biggest drama I ever had on Twitch was
based on an editor and I won't get into
the drama that happened but I actually
said that I didn't like neovim and was
somewhat attacked for saying that um and
at the time it was it was nothing
personal it was just like I don't think
it's a good editor here's
reasons and um yeah I was I was totally
attacked and it it blew up into drama
and I said bad things and they said bad
things and we ended up fighting can I
just I just want to end this video with
a plea to everyone if you are going to
profess that your editor is the best
rather than starting with the conclusion
that everybody else editor sucks and
yours is the best maybe maybe start with
the point BYO comparison about why and
by the way the reason I can't I I I did
this I have a 12o I did I I did a full
evaluation of do ofm and I have a 12
point BYO evaluation of DM and why I
don't like it and I actually went into
it wanting to like it and um and I
actually may still be convinced to use
the if I'm on the same system all the
time which I frequently am so uh I mean
there's some people who think Vim is is
is too big a departure from VI there's a
and Unix users and people like that who
think Vim is a bastardization and nobody
should use it you should only use VI
which is a separate thing and at least
understanding the difference between
those things I think is valuable for
everyone so if so if you if you're going
to engage in the my editor is better
than yours I would encourage you to ask
the other person what their priorities
are right get to understand them so that
you can empathize with what they do and
every time when I look back at the drama
that I had the people that were pushing
for neovim the hardest were people that
were doing mostly development so these
would be people in the same category as
vs code people and um you know intellig
even Eclipse people and and you know
emac people because they were on the
same computer these are also the same
people that were pushing heavily to have
Linux on the desktop like I have a
desktop I'm going to put whatever I want
on there I'm going to build up my own
development workstation and I have total
control of that right so once I
understood where they were coming from I
could get behind that decision a lot
more but where I was coming from which
is as a hacker as a hacker and as a an
Ops person I need to be good on any
system any time that means I need to use
and leverage the tools that are on the
system and so my priorities were
dramatically different from the
priorities of somebody that was pushing
for Neo him like that somebody who's got
their one system right I need to get
good with with hacking into a system
where I don't even have TTY access I
can't even use an editor at all all
right I got to be able to to you know Ed
this or I've got to be able to to cat
this or you know whatever there's there
there are the point I'm trying to make
is please seek to understand before you
have a fight about something completely
stupid because one of you wants to do
one thing and the other one wants to do
something completely different you know
don't don't waste your time fighting
about that it's also the same this
argument goes for languages it goes for
the desktop it goes for any one of these
things right people are so willing and
myself included I've been very guilty of
this they're so willing to tell you what
to do um without seeking to understand
what it is you want to do or be and I'm
just going to ask you in the editor Wars
and the feelings have been hurt
marriages have been lost over you know
preferences about editors let alone tabs
versus spaces which we'll talk about
another
time so so the takeaway from is um I
personally I'm just going to net it out
personally I think every technologist on
the planet should at least be able to be
proficient with vs code because it's the
most popular it's the most likely you're
going to run into that on the job and
with a terminal editor specifically Vim
um VI and Vim but Vim primarily right so
because these are things that come on
the system all the time so for the
beginner boost we will be learning vs
code and Vim that those are the two
thing now if you want to do anything
else with that and you want to take it
in into another angle and you've got
other stuff you want I got no problem
with that I do feel very strongly that
every single technologist on the
planet um no matter what flavor of of
technical career you have must
understand to be proficient with BS code
and be proficient with Bim at least
enough to be proficient with it when
asked to use it if if if if you were to
go to a job interview and they were to
ask you have you ever I mean have you
ever used Vim or have you ever used vs
code and you were to say no I've never
tried them I think it's pretty fair to
say You can disagree with me in the
comments but I think it's pretty fair to
say that that they would be shocked they
would be shocked most most interviewers
would be shocked that you have not even
tried it yet right so so we're going to
use the the the two most important most
popular most fundamental in my opinion
editors on the planet for technology and
I I got no problem with you disagreeing
with these selections right um if I were
to interview somebody and they said they
use emac and I said but have you ever
used vim and can you use it they say
yeah I can I don't want to though I
don't like it I'm like oh okay you know
that kind of would make me perk up and
think hey this person's actually
evaluated um why this editor is good and
and that's why knowing what editor
somebody uses is kind of insightful
because if you know that they're using
goand and they know vs code is a thing
but they want to use goand because goand
does X and Y and Z better that that that
is a very well-informed very
autodidactic technologist that I would
be curious to to to know more about them
so so that that's where I'm coming from
uh that's a very long video but I mean
what are you going to expect from a
video about editors right